A Guide to the Records of the Virginia State Navy Board, 1776-1782.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia State Navy Board,
1776-1782.
The Library of Virginia
54306
Navy Board.
9 volumes.
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Use microfilm when available.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Historical Information
Revolutionary naval operations were initially under the control of the Committee of Safety. The May 1776 Convention, however, passed an ordinance "establishing a Board of Commissioners to Superintend and Direct the Naval Affairs of the Colony." The Board, given very broad powers, was "generally to superintend and direct all matters and things to the navy relating," including construction, labor, and supply. The ordinance named Thomas Whiting, John Hutchings, Champion Travis, Thomas Newton and George Webb as Commissioners (Chap. XV, May 1776). The members selected Whiting as chairman, a position he held throughout the Board's existence.
In May 1779 the General Assembly passed acts creating a Board of War, with authority "to appoint a commissioner of the Navy," and discontinuing the Navy Board, as its duties and offices were to be performed by the newly established boards of war and trade. (Chapters III and L)
On June 30, 1779, James Maxwell was appointed to the position of Commissioner of the Navy. Maxwell retained this position even after the Board of War was abolished in May 1780, being appointed thereto by the governor and council. The office was, however, abolished by the November 1781 legislative session in "An act for regulating the military and naval arrangements of this state." (Chap VIII)
Scope and Content
Navy Board records include Accounts, 1776-1782; Journal, 1780; Ledger, 1776-1779; Letterbook, 1776-1777; List of captains and lieutenants, 1776-1779; List of Officers and Seamen of the State Navy and Marines, 1776-1779; Minute books, 1777-1778; Order books, 1776-1779; and Proceedings, 1784.
For additional records see the Governor's Executive Papers for this time period; General Correspondence of the Virginia Navy Board (Acc. 51711).
Contents List
- Accounts, 1776 Feb-1782 Mar., Extent: 1 v.
  This account book includes general entry of debits and credits, some to specific ships per order of their captains, some to individuals, and some to public operations, such as the Public Store and Ropewalk. (Accession 54306)
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 302.
- Journal of the Commissioner of the Navy, 1780 July 21-Dec 19, Extent: 1 v.
  This journal is a record of business of the Navy Board kept by Commissioner James Maxwell, regarding the administration of the Navy. Includes orders for clothing and supplies to the Commissary of Stores; orders for warrants of payment; notes on letters written to the Governor (and his reply) and officers; leaves of absence granted; and notes on discharges, among others. Also included is a photostat copy of an Index to the Journal.(Accession 54306)
- Ledger, 1776 July 10-1779 July 10., Extent: 1 v.
  This ledger provides a listing of debits and credits for naval expenses for supplying ships. (Accession 54306)
  - Ledger, 1776 July 15-1779 Jan.
- Letterbook, 1776 July 15-1777 Oct 9, Extent: 1 v.
  Letterbook includes copies of outgoing correspondence from the Navy Board, signed mainly by Thomas Whiting as the commissioner. These letters were written from Williamsburg regarding ships' supplies, requests for reports from ships' captains and delivery orders to suppliers. Also includes a separate 5 p. index. (Accession 54306)
- List of captains and lieutenants in the Virginia Navy, 1776-1779, Extent: 2 p.
  This list is divided by rank and there are only two captains listed. The lieutenants are listed by date commissioned between 25 Nov 1776 and 4 Aug 1779. The list of lieutenants indicates whether they were recommended as first lieutenant and whether or not they resigned. (Accession 44310)
- Officers and Seamen of the State Navy and Marines, 1776-1779., Extent: 1 v.
  This volume includes three lists of naval and marine personnel appointed by the Committee of Safety and the Council.
  The first list includes a list officers of the navy and marines, 1776-1777, arranged alphbetically by surname initial. Entries include date commissioned, rank, and name of vessel to which they were assigned, if applicable.
  The second list includes an unorganized list of officers from which the first section was created.
  The third list includes a list of Navy vessels, 1776-1779. Entries identify the names and rank of their officers and crew, and in some instances dates of entry and discharge from service are given..
  These lists are in the hand of John H. Smith and were prepared from pay rolls, vouchers, miscellaneous papers and entries in journals of the Committee of Safety and Council of State. Index is only applicable to the third list. (Accession 54306)
- Minute books, 1777 Mar 26-1777 Sept 10., Extent: 2 v.
  These Minute Books contain minutes of the meetings of the Navy Board, in which they address supply needs and issue orders for the delivery of supplies and building of vessels. These proceedings of the business conducted by the Navy Board are signed by the senior commissioner present. Period covered in v.1: March 26 - October 7, 1777 and February 14 - September 10, 1778; v.2: October 8, 1777 - February 13, 1778.(Accession 54306)
  - Minute book, 1777 Mar 26-Oct 7; 1778 Feb 14-Sept 10..
  - Minute book, 1777 Oct 8-1778 Feb 13..
- Order books, 1776 July 23-1779 June 23., Extent: 2 v.
  Order books contain orders issued by the Navy Board in their administration of the Navy and the business of supplying vessels with goods and labor. Names of the members of the Navy Board precede. Period covered: v.1: July 23, 1776 - February 27, 1779; v.2: March 6 - June 23, 1779.(Accession 54306)
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 301.
  - Order book, 1776 July 23-1779 Feb 27.
  - Order book, 1779 Mar 6-June 23..
- Proceedings of the Navy Board, 1784., Extent: 1 p.
  Proceedings of a board of officers, late of the State Line and Navy, regarding the examination of a list of officers of the Navy. The proceedings include the list of officers of the State Navy which provides the name of the officer, their rank, and date commissioned. The list is signed by James Baron, President, and Governor Benjamin Harrison. (Accession 44303)